Hello, this is Dr.
Eugene Petkoff from the
Department of
Biomedical Sciences, and
today is my pleasure
to welcome you to the
Atelectasis and
Pulmonary Edema Lecture.
On this slide, I have
mentioned all the
objectives of today's
lecture, which might help
you to organize your
study. we will discuss
the pathogenesis of
atelectasis and respiratory
distress syndrome
of newborns. Then we
will compare the
hemodynamic pulmonary edema
and the microvascular
injury-associated
pulmonary edema. In
addition, we will explain the
ARDS, acute respiratory
distress syndrome.
Please note that,
unless mentioned
otherwise, all the
images and information
included in this
presentation are
from Robbins and
Cotran Pathologic
Basis of Disease,
the 10th edition.
Aphylectasis. It
refers either to an
incomplete expansion
of the lungs as seen
in neonates, or the
collapse of a previously
inflated lung,
resulting in areas
of poorly aerated
pulmonary parenchyma.
Please note
that atelectasis
is not a disease per se.
It represents a
manifestation of an
underlying disease, and
there are several types
of atelectasis. We
have obstructive or
resorptive athelactasis
and non-obstructive
athelactasis, which
can be described as
compressive and
contraction athelactasis.
Obstructive
athelactasis is seen as
after obstruction of
an IRA by an inhaled
foreign body, mucus
plugs or a tumor.
The circulating
blood will resorb the
gas from alveoli
in these settings
Excessive secretions
with formation
of mucus plugs are
seen in bronchial
asthma, chronic
bronchitis,
bronchiectasis and in
postoperative states
Non-obstructive
compression of alectasis
This entity develops
if significant volumes
of fluid, such as
transudate, exudate,
blood, or air,
accumulate within pleural
cavity, and lung volumes
will be decreased.
In these conditions,
mediastymal will
shift away from the
affected lung. On
the other hand,
non-obstructive
contraction or cicatricial
atelectasis is in
an association with
focal and generalized
pulmonary or
pleural fibrosis,
which will prevent
full lung expansion.
Please note
that in general,
significant atelectasis
reduces oxygenation
and predisposes
to infection.
Also, except in cases
caused by fibrosis,
athelectasis is a
reversible condition.
With any type of
athelectasis which
presents with pain
on the affected
side of the chest
and dyspnea,
they have cyanosis
and the breath
sounds are either
decreased or absent.
Also, there is
dullness to percussion
over the affected
lung field.
In addition,
trachea and
the heart will
deviate towards
the affected side.
Afflectasis is confirmed
by arterial blood
gas evaluation, CT
scans, or chest X-ray.
Flexible fibro-optic
bronchoscopy might
also be performed
in some patients.
Therapy in these patients
consists of chest
physiotherapy, including
postural drainage,
chest percussion
and vibration, as
well as forced
expiratory exercises.
These patients
might also be
treated with continuous
positive airway
pressure and
bronchodilators.
In some patients
surgery might be
required, especially
in those with
a chronic evolution
in which segmental
resection might
be performed.
Now let's talk about
each type of atelectasia.
Obstruction or resorption
of atelectasis.
It is caused by a mucus
or a mucopurulent plug.
As mentioned before,
this is seen in
bronchial asthma,
bronchiectasis or in chronic
bronchitis. It is
also seen in patients
with foreign body
inhalation and might be
determined by an intra
-bronchial tumor or
an enlarged lymph node
seen at this level.
By the way, during
your clinical rotations
you will hear the term
lobar atelectasis.
This is caused
by obstruction of
a lobar bronchus.
You also encounter in
some patient's
segmental athelectasis.
This is caused
by obstruction
in the segmental
bronchus.
The endoscopic
image seen on this
slide shows a total
obstruction of the
left main bronchus
by a mucus plug.
On this slide, we
have mentioned the
most important elements
of obstruction,
resorption, athelectasis
pathogenesis.
In brief, after
bronchial obstruction,
the blood
circulating in the
alveolar capillary
membrane will
absorb the gas
from the alveoli.
This gas absorption will
induce retraction
of the lung.
Subsequently, in
few hours, the
affected alveoli
will be airless.
However, the
blood flow will
reach an airless
unventilated lung
and arterial
hypoxemia ensues.
The blood leaving
the lung will
not be oxygenated.
Meantime,
secretions and
dead cells will
accumulate in the
alveoli, preventing
the collapse
of this lung.
However,
the surrounding
healthy lung will
distend and there
is a mediastinal
shift towards the
affected lung.
In addition,
the diaphragm will
be elevated while
the chest wall
will become flat.
On the right side
of this slide there
is a drawing
which illustrates
the mechanism of
this condition
highlighting the
retraction of the lung.
Compression athelectasis.
As mentioned previously
compression athelectasis
is determined by
a pleural effusion
associated with cardiac
failure or cancer.
It is also determined
by accumulation of
blood or air in the
pleural cavity, more
specifically hemothorax
or pneumothorax.
It is also seen in
conditions in which there
is an elevated diaphragm
such as in bedridden
patients, after
surgery, and in ositis.
The drawing included in
this slide summarizes
the pathogenesis
of this condition,
specifically accumulation
of the fluid,
blood, or air within
pleural cavity.
Please note that
in compression
aphelactasis, the
mediastinum and trachea are
pushed away towards
the healthy lung.
On X-ray, there is an
increased transparency
of the lung field
and a hyper-resonance
is recorded on
physical examination.
Contraction aphylectasis
This is also known
as cicatrization
aphylectasis and is
determined by a reduction
of lung volumes following
extensive severe
parenchyma scarring.
This type of defective
healing is seen in
lung tuberculosis,
which is a granulomatous
inflammation of the
lung parenchyma.
Severe parenchyma
scarring is also
seen in necrotizing
pneumonia.
Anyway, the most
important morphological
anomaly seen in
this patient,
apart from lung
parenchyma scarring,
is bronchial
scarring, leading to
significant narrowing
of the bronchial lumen.
The image included
in this slide
shows the left
and right lungs
removed during an
autopsy of a patient
with contraction
athelectasis.
As you might see,
the left lung and
the middle and the
lower lobes of the
right lung are
totally collapsed,
while the upper lobe
of the right lung
seem to be inflated.
Now I would like to
discuss a special
form of athelectasis,
the respiratory
distress syndrome
in newborns, RDS,
also known as neonatal
respiratory distress
syndrome or hyaline
membrane disease.
What's happening
in this setting?
Well at birth the
lungs inflate with air
and the airways remain
open due to surfactant.
Surfactant is a
mixture of lipids,
proteins, glycoproteins,
lecithin and
sphingomyelin secreted
by pneumocytes type 2.
This factor maintains
the stability of
pulmonary tissue by
reducing the surface
tension in the small
-caliber airways.
This decreased surface
tension prevents the
collapse of these
airways on expiration.
Regarding the production
of surfactant, it
begins around 28
weeks in utero and it
reaches its peak
around the 35th week of
pregnancy and is modulated
by glucocorticoids.
Therefore, if a
delivery takes place
before the term,
the newborns must be
treated with
glucocorticoids, which
would increase
the synthesis of
surfactant and newborn
********* babies.
RDS is seen not
only in prematurity,
but also in babies from
mothers with
diabetes mellitus.
Anyway, the newborns
with RDS will present
with harsh respiratory
noises or grunting,
tachymnea or
fast breathing,
intercostal
retraction, and an
abnormal lecithin
to sphingomyelin
ratio of less than 1.5.
Despite modern therapies,
RDS is the most
common single cause
of death in the first
month of life in the
Western countries.
RDS is associated
with blindness,
bronchopulmonary
dysplasia,
cardiac anomalies such as
patent ductus arteriosus,
intraventricular
hemorrhage,
and hypoglycemia.
The characteristic
histopathology seen
in newborns who died
from RDS represented
the basis for the
old label of this
condition as hyaline
membrane disease.
The right side
microphotographs shows
a hematoxylineosin
stained tissue
section taken from
a baby with RDS.
The lung is congested,
showing numerous
dilated capillaries,
but more importantly
the alveoli are lined
by hyaline membranes
which appear as
eosinophilic pink and are
made of fibrin and
epithelial dead cells.
Overall, the lung
is collapsed.
As a result of
deposition of hyaline
membranes, blood which
passes through lungs, is
unable to pick up
oxygen and unload CO2.
Blood oxygen level
falls and CO2 increases,
resulting in
acidosis and hypoxia.
Promoedema represents
the accumulation of
excessive interstitial
fluid in the alveoli.
This large amount of
fluid accumulation
results either as a
result of hemodynamic
abnormalities or after
microvascular injury.
Therefore, we have two
major types of edema,
hemodynamic
edema and edema
associated with
microvascular injury.
Hemodynamic edema is
seen in congestive
heart failure and other
conditions associated
with an increased
left heart pressure
and impaired heart
contractility, such
as coronary artery
disease, hypertension,
valvular disease,
and dilated
cardiomyopathy, various
metabolic conditions
such as hypothyroidism,
myocarditis,
ventricular hypertrophy
and outflow obstruction.
In all these conditions
there is an increased
hydrostatic pressure
and as a result there
is an elevated pulmonary
venous pressure.
In this setting there
is decreased cardiac
output and a reduced
renal blood flow.
This would
activate the renal
angiotensinal dosterol
pathway and the
sympathetic nervous
system, leading
to sodium and
water retention.
Overall, there is an
increased fluid load
in the body and a
transfer of this fluid
from the capillaries to
the interstitium with
formation of lung
and peripheral edema.
Accumulation of
excess fluid is
also determined by
hypoalbuminemia.
This is determined
by loss of oncotic
pressure as seen in
liver failure, protein
losing enteropathy,
and nephrotic syndrome.
The The other
type of edema, the
microvascular injury
associated pulmonary
edema, results
after primary injury
to the alveolar
capillary endothelium.
It is characterized by
leakage of fluid and
protein in the lung
interstitium and is
seen in acute respiratory
distress syndrome,
bacterial pneumonia,
radiation, lung
trauma, liquid
aspiration, high
-altitude disease,
opioid overdose,
and inhaled gases
oxygen injury.
Hemodynamic pulmonary
edema. This type of
pulmonary edema is
seen in the US in more
than 83,000 cases per
1 million people with
heart failure and low
ejection fraction.
The mortality rate
at six years follow
-up is 85% in those
with congestive heart
failure which develop
pulmonary edema.
Edema is seen in
the early stages
in the basal areas
of lower lobes.
This is explained
by the fact
that hydrostatic pressure
has very high values
and is the greatest
in the basal areas
of lower lobes.
At sub-stage,
edema fluid will
escape into the alveoli
and the patient
will cough a froth.
The microscopic
image on this slide
shows a lung section
transversally.
The pattern seen
here indicates
a fluid-filled
foaming lung, which
suggests an
increased volume.
In this lung, both
the ventilation and
the oxygen diffusion
were impaired.
Overall,
all of these abnormalities
would promote
a good harboring
environment for bacteria,
inducing further tissue
damage and pneumonia.
On this slide, both
microscopic images
represent a case of
hemodynamic pulmonary edema.
On the left side,
you may note the
alveolar spaces
filled with the finely
granule pale pink
proteinaceous material.
The right side image
reveals alveolar
capillaries within
alveolar walls.
These are dilated.
There are also
microhemorrhages
and hemocidrine
-laden macrophages.
These cells are also
known as heart failure
cells and suggest long
-standing pulmonary
congestion, as seen
in mitral stenosis.
Although not represented
here, fibrosis
and thickening of
the alveolar walls
cause the lung to
become firm and brown.
These changes are
characteristic for the
late stage of hemodynamic
pulmonary edema
and are labeled as
brown in duration.
Overall, these
changes will
predispose to
pulmonary infection.
Mycovascular
injury associated
pulmonary edema and acute
respiratory distress
syndrome, ARDS.
As mentioned before,
in these patients,
we see an inflammatory
exudate in the
interstitial space and
into the alveoli, which
results after pulmonary
vascular endothelium
damage or injury to
both the alveolar,
epithelium, and
vascular endothelium.
Injury-related
alveolar edema is
also a crucial
feature of ARDS,
acute respiratory
distress syndrome.
ARDS oftentimes
is a serious and
fatal pathological
condition.
Anyway, let's
explain the ARDS.
ARDS. This is defined
as an acute and rapidly
progressive hypoxia
with bilateral
pulmonary edema resulting
from alveolar injury.
Alveolar injury
is determined by
pulmonary and
systemic conditions.
Please note that
ARDS is very serious
and 40% of patients
will die within
28 days from onset.
as a result of
superimposed
infection, sepsis, and
multiple organ
dysfunction syndrome.
If the patient
survives, the
lung shows
interstitial fibrosis
and chronic
pulmonary disease.
ARDS clinical features.
Patients with ARDS
will present with
severe dyspnea and
tachymnea associated
with worsening
respiratory failure,
hypoxemia, and cyanosis.
Respiratory
acidosis would also
be noted in
these patients.
Hypoxemia is not
always corrected by
oxygen therapy due to
a ventilation-perfusion
mismatch and a
decreased compliance.
By the way, the
ratio between partial
pressure of oxygen
and fraction of
inspired oxygen is
decreased below 300,
suggesting
intrapulmonary shunting
and diffusion
abnormalities.
However, very early
in this disease
the lungs will
become stiff due
to a functional
loss of surfactant.
Therefore, the
patient will require
intubation to
maintain at a
reasonable level
the gas exchanges.
The x-ray will show
diffused bilateral
infiltrates, opacities,
but ARDS is a diagnosis
of exclusion, which
can be remembered
by the mnemonic formula
ARDS, in which A
stands for abnormal x
-ray, R for respiratory
failure, D for
decreased partial
pressure of oxygen to
inspired pressure oxygen,
and S for symptoms of
respiratory failure,
not due to congestive
heart failure.
Regarding the treatment,
we have to stress that
treating the underlying
disease and
providing mechanical
ventilation to maintain
the gas exchanges are
of paramount importance
in these patients.
ARDS etiology.
ARDS is a rapid
onset pathological
condition, which is
determined by direct alveolar
injury as seen in
viral infections
and inhalation of
various toxic solvents.
A direct alveolar
injury might be seen in
some patients as a
side effect of oxygen
therapy. ARDS is also
associated with some
systemic conditions
such as septic shock,
hypovolemic and
hemorrhagic shock,
pancreatitis and
afterburns, abdominal
surgeries and
narcotic overdose.
ARDS is divided in three
physiopathological
stages or phases.
An exudative phase
determined by destruction
of epithelial
interstitial endothelial
barrier which promotes
accumulation of fluid
in interstitium and
air spaces is followed
by a proliferative
phase characterized by
regeneration of a
damaged alveolar barrier.
The last phase
of ARDS is the
fibrotic phase in
which there is impaired
removal of
alveolar collagen.
This collagen was
produced by the
fibroblasts that
have infiltrated the
interstitium during the
proliferative phase.
This collagen has a
negative effect limiting
functional recovery
in these patients.
ARDS pathogenesis. There
are three phases of ARDS.
Initially there is an
exerative acute phase
which lasts from day
one to seven. This
is followed after
the first week by a
proliferative organizing
subacute phase which
is seen up to the
third week of disease.
There is also a fibrotic
or chronic phase
described usually
after the third week.
Now let's describe
the first phase,
the exudative
acute phase.
Regardless the
cause, initially
the alveolar
are damaged by a
neutrophil-induced
inflammation.
This alveolar insult
results in subsequent
release of cytokines
and there is
additional recruitment
of neutrophils which
are in turn activated
and release reactive
oxygen species and
prophesies. These are
very toxic products
for all the tissues.
Macrophages are
activated as well.
The cytokines reactive
oxygen species
and prophesies
will induce further
endothelial capillary
damage, will
increase capillary
permeability,
promoting intralveolar
hemorrhage and
pulmonary edema.
There is additional
microcapillary
coagulation.
However, the protein
-rich fluid accumulated
will interact with
the surfactant,
which is released by
pneumocyte type 2.
This results in formation
of hyaline membranes
and decreased
pulmonary compliance.
After the first week
in proliferative
phase, the pneumocytes
type 2 will start
regenerating and
manufacturing surfactant.
Surfactant will
restore lung compliance
and this is of
paramount importance
for the recovery
of the patient.
Type 2 pneumocytes
will also
help the recovery
by draining,
removing the
alveolar edema.
In parallel, there
is also proliferation
of interstitial
myofibroblasts and endothelial
vascular proliferation,
suggesting the
beginning of post
-inflammatory healing.
After three weeks,
all these changes
are followed by
interstitial and
intra-alveolar
fibrosis. Endotelial
vascular proliferation
described
in the proliferative
phase in some cases
leads to obliteration
of microcapillaries
with tissue
remodeling and
refractory rigidity
of alveoli.
Anyway, for your
convenience, I have
included on this slide
the drawing which
summarizes the most
important pathological
changes seen in
the capillaries and
interstitium according
to each phase of ARDS.
As you can see the
exudative phase represents
an inflammation associated
with interstitial
edema and activation
of coagulation.
In addition, there
is infiltration and
further recruitment
of neutrophils.
In proliferative
phase, the process of
pneumocyte type 2
regeneration is seen
in parallel with
a significant
proliferation of
endothelial barrier cells as
well as interstitial
myofibroblasts.
Ultimately, the fibrotic
phase is associated
with obliteration
of capillaries
and interstitial intra
-alveolar fibrosis.
ARDS morphology.
On this slide, the
image represents
a lung which was
dissected
transversally. This is a
lung in the exudative
phase of ARDS.
In this phase, the
lungs are heavy,
firm, red, and
boggy. This pattern
is explained by the
interstitial intra
-alveolar edema
and inflammation
which might be seen
microscopically.
ARDS histology in
acute exudative stage.
As you might
see on the upper
microscopic image,
the alveolar walls
are lined by waxy
hyaline membranes.
These membranes
are made of fibrin
-rich edema fluid
mixed with remnants
of necrotic
epithelial cells.
There is also expansion
of the interstitium
with macrophages
and inflammation.
As mentioned before,
in proliferative phase
neomocyte type II
proliferate and
granulation tissue forms
in the alveolar walls
and spaces. In most
cases, the granulation
tissue resolves,
leaving minimal
functional impairment.
Sometimes, however,
fibrotic thickening of
the alveolar
septa ensues.
The lower microscopic
images on this
slide labeled C and
D represent lung
sections stained with
hematoxylin eosin
obtained from lung
biopsy of an ARDS
patient during
proliferative phase.
In both images,
you can see
proliferation and
hyperplasia of
pneumocytes type 2, as
well as interstitial
fibrosis and
proliferation.
There is also
proliferation
of myofibroblasts.
These two microscopic
images represent
lung sections stained
with myotoxylineosin
obtained from lung
biopsy of an ARDS
patient during fibrotic
phase. The left
side image shows a
dense collagenous
fibrosis with destruction
of alveoli. The
right side image
reveals extensive
fibroblastic proliferation
in the interstitium
as well as some
hyaline membranes.
In conclusion, today
we have completed
all the session
objectives. We have
discussed athelactasis,
its various forms,
their morphology and
major etiological
factors.
Subsequently, we
have discussed the
respiratory distress
syndrome of newborn,
including the role
of surfactant in
the etiopathogenesis
of this condition.
Then we have presented
the major forms
of pulmonary edema,
the hemodynamic
pulmonary edema, and
the microvascular
injury-associated
pulmonary edema.
Hemodynamic pulmonary
edema is seen in
congestive heart
failure or in conditions
associated with increased
left heart pressure.
In both these
settings the
hydrostatic pressure
is increased.
There is decreased
cardiac output
and the renin-angiotensin
-aldosterone pathway
is activated
with retention of
sodium and water
which increases
venous pressure
and results in
edema formation.
Hemodynamic pulmonary
edema is also
seen in patients
with low levels of
albumin with loss of
oncotic pressure, as
noted in liver
failure, protein-losing
enteropathy, and
nephrotic syndrome.
We have also discussed
the mycovascular
injury-associated
pulmonary edema,
which is determined
by injury to
the alveolar
capillary endothelium.
We have explained
the etiology and at
the end of the session
we have debated the
ARDS, acute respiratory
distress syndrome,
which is a diagnosis
of exclusion.
ARDS results after
a significant
damage of alveolar
epithelium.
It has three distinct
physiopathological
phases, an exudative
phase followed by
a proliferative and
a fibrotic phase,
and is characterized
by abnormal chest
X-ray, respiratory
failure, a decreased
ratio of partial
pressure of oxygen to
a fraction of
inspired oxygen, and
symptoms of respiratory
failure in the absence
of heart failure
or fluid overload.
Thank you very much
for your attention
and good luck
with your studies.
Please let me know if
you have any questions
at the following address
e.petcu.nyit.edu.
Once again,
thank you very
much for your attention.